[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-seven]
[第三十七集]
My fellow students.
同学们
We are all witnesses of the May Fourth Movement.
咱们大家都是五四运动的亲历者
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
The May Fourth Movement was great.
五四运动是伟大的
Here, I want to ask you a question.
那么我想问问同学价
Why is the May Fourth Movement great?
五四运动究竞伟大在什么地方
Large scale, and large number of people.
规模大 人数多
Also all walks of life took part.
然后 各行各业都参加了
Qunxian is right.
群先说得没错
[He Mengxiong, Visiting student at Peking University] [Deng Zhongxia, styled Zhongxie, Student at Peking University]
[何孟雄 北京大学旁听生] [邓中夏 字 仲澥 北京大学学生]
But I think
但是我以为
the most important thing about the May Fourth Movement,
五四运动最重要的一点
is that it is an anti-feudal
就是它是一场既反对封建主义
[Zhao Shiyan, styled Qinsheng, Student at The High School Affiliated to Beijing Normal University] [Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
[赵世炎 字 琴生 北京高等师范附中学生] [陈延年 陈独秀长子]
and anti-imperialist
又反对帝国主义的
mass patriotic self-reliance movement.
群众性的爱国自救运动
These few days,
最近几天
I was buried in thoughts sitting in the ancestral temple of Hanyu.
我在韩文公祠里头面壁反思
I realized something.
我悟出了一个道理
If China seeks development,
中国要想求发展
then the path of Russian Revolution should be adopted.
恐怕要走俄国革命的道路
That is the inspiration of the May Fourth Movement.
这是五四运动给我的启示
Everyone is here today.
今天大伙都来了
Just in time, I propose,
正好 我提议
let's restart the reading class in the Red Building here.
我们把红楼读书班再恢复起来
Let's study together and think thoroughly
大家好好研究一下
which path can lead to a better China.
未来的中国应该走哪条道路
Sounds good?
好不好
Yes.
好 好
Brother Yannian.
延年兄
Why don't we have a debate
不如咱们就在这五峰山上
between Marxism and anarchism
来一场轰轰烈烈的马克思主义
right here in Wufengshan?
跟无政府主义的大论战
Do you dare to take it?
你敢接招吗
Of course I will.
那有什么不敢的
To the very end.
奉陪到底
Okay!
好
Speaking of which.
你们说到论战
Mr. Hu Shi
胡适先生啊
published an article
最近在《每周评论》上
in the latest "Weekly Review",
发表了一篇文章
titled
名字叫作
"Focus more on actual problems, less on abstract doctrine."
《多研究些问题 少谈些主义》
It caused a wide response.
引起了不小的反响
Lan Gongwu,
蓝公武
the one from the research department,
研究系的蓝公武
also published an article
也在《国民公报》上
in the "National Gazette".
发表了一篇文章
It's called "Problems and Doctrine".
名字叫作《问题与主义》
These two articles caused quite a controversy now.
他与胡适的文章引起了论战
Before I came here,
我来这儿之前啊
I visited Mr. Zhongfu.
去看望过仲甫先生
He's a little ambiguous on this issue.
他呢有些模棱两可
He doesn't agree with Mr. Hu Shi,
好像既不太同意胡适先生的观点
but he also doesn't think Lan Gongwu's words are convincing enough.
也觉得蓝公武没有什么说服力
So he asked me to turn to Mr. Shouchang for some advice.
所以 想让我请守常先生
Please take a look at this article.
来看看这篇文章
Students.
同学们
I think it is too early for a debate
我觉得现在开展马克思主义
between Marxism
与无政府主义的辩论
and anarchism.
有点为时尚早
I suggest
我建议
we should discuss this first.
我们先讨论一下
This problem and doctrine from Mr. Hu Shi.
胡适先生的这篇问题与主义吧
To Mr. Shizhi.
适之先生
I have read your article
读了先生在本报
from the paper that came out on the 31st.
三十一号发表的那篇论文
The title is
题目是
"Focus more on actual problems, less on abstract doctrine."
《多研究些问题 少谈些主义》
Inspired by which, I have some thoughts now.
就发生了一些感想
Some
其中有的
may relate to your view,
或可与先生的主张互相发明
some is what I want to tell the whole society.
有的是我们对社会的告白
Now I write them all down.
现在把他一一写出
Please share your thoughts on this with me.
请先生指正
[Peking University]
[北京大学]
Fellow students.
各位同学
I asked you to stay at school.
把你们留在学校
Because there's something ongoing now that might affect you.
是因为有一件事情正在酝酿当中
Everyone knows,
大家都知道
during the May Fourth movement,
五四期间
Mr. Mu Ouchu from Shanghai
上海的穆耦初先生
made a donation to Peking University,
向我们的北京大学捐款
a huge amount of money.
十几万的大洋
But the student union didn't take it.
但是学生会没有要
Now, my senior alumnus, Mr. Jiang Menglin
而现在我的师兄蒋梦麟先生
entrusted by Mr. Cai,
受蔡先生的委托
manages Peking University.
代管北京大学
So I asked him.
我就向他提出
Can we use this money?
能不能用这些钱
Can we use it
能不能用这一笔钱
to support students with potential in Peking University
丢资助在北京大学有潜力的学生
to study abroad in the United States?
去美国留学深造
Mr. Jiang agreed.
蒋先生同意了
You here are all possible candidates.
各位都是考察对象
So I kept you late today.
所以把各位留在了学校里面
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
However, there is another reason
那其实今天我把大家叫来呢
for having you all here today.
要谈的是另外一件事情
I believe that
各位已经看了
you have all read my article
我在《每周评论》
from the "Weekly Review" that came out on the 31st.
第三十一号写的
"Focus more on actual problems, less on abstract doctrine"
《多研究些问题 少谈些主义》
Everyone here played vital role in the May Fourth Movement.
各位都是五四干将
I want to talk to you about this article.
所以我要和你们谈一谈这篇文章
Since the May Fourth Movement,
自五四以来
many people
很多新的分子
don't talk about specific political issues.
闭口不谈具体的政治问题
Instead, they only blabber about Marxism
反而去高谈什么马克思主义
and anarchism.
还有无政府主义
I can't watch it.
我看不了了
I can't stand it either.
也受不了了
Because I am a believer in experimentalism.
因为我个人是实验主义的信徒
I felt provoked, so I want to talk about politics now.
所以发愤想要谈政治
Which resulted in that article.
于是就有了这篇文章
I think there is a great danger now.
我认为现在有一个很大的危险啊
That is the empty talk on imported doctrine,
那就是空谈外来进口的主义
and the clueless bias towards theory from foreign papers.
偏向外来纸上的学说
Instead of actually investigating
而不去实际考察
on what China today really needs.
现今的中国他到底需要的是什么
Students.
同学们
I have read the article
我看了胡适先生的那篇
"Focus more on actual problems, less on abstract doctrine"
《多研究些问题 少谈些主义》
from Mr. Hu Shi.
的文章了
I think there are several important issues
我觉得有几个重要的问题
that I need to clarify with you.
我需要跟大家澄清一下
So I wrote this article
所以 我就作了这篇文章
with this title here.
取了这个题目
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
Why is that called reconsideration?
那为什么叫再论
Because Lan Gongwu has already published his article "Problems and Doctrine"
因为有蓝公武在《国民公报》上
in the "National Gazette".
发表了《问题与主义》一文
So my one
所以我的这一篇
is the second consideration.
就只能叫再论了
First of all,
首先一点啊
I disagree with his view
我不同意胡适先生
that we should focus less on doctrine.
少谈主义的观点
Given the current situation in China,
因为现在的中国
the most urgent matter for us
我们当务之急要做的事情
is to find a way to save the country.
是寻找一条挽救国家沉沦的道路
Without doctrine and theory,
没有主义和科学理论
there is no direction.
就等于没有方向
Looking for a new road without a guide flag,
寻找新路而没有引路的旗帜
we may go down a wrong path or worse,
就可能走上一条歧路
a dead end.
甚至是一条死路
Therefore, doctrine
所以说主义
is crucial.
是非常重要的
Sir.
先生
I have read Mr. Hu Shi's article.
我看过胡适先生的文章
He said he deeply felt
他说他深深地感觉到了
the danger behind doctrine.
主义的危险
That danger Mr. Hu Shi talked about,
胡适先生说到主义的危险
I'm afraid it's not caused by doctrine.
我觉得恐怕不是主义本身带来的
What brought it then?
是什么带来的
Those who only blabber about doctrine.
是那些空谈它的人带来的
I remember Mr. Zhongfu once said that
我记得仲甫先生曾经说过一句话
what China today desperately needs
说 当今的中国
is a theory that can save the nation.
最需要的就是救国的理论
So what is theory, students?
那么理论是什么 同学们
Theory is doctrine.
理论就是主义呀
If China wants to develop,
所以中国要想求发展
we must find an advanced theory,
必须要找到一个先进的理论
a doctrine.
就是主义
Mr. Hu Shi said that
胡适先生说
there is fake socialism.
社会主义有冒牌的
So we can't talk about it.
所以不能高谈
I don't agree with this either.
关于这一点我也不敢苟同
It is true that now
诚然 当今的社会
there are all kinds of socialism being spread around.
的确流行着各种各样的社会主义
There is the scientific socialism
有我们宣传的
which we promote.
科学社会主义
There is also Anfu Club's socialism,
安福系的社会主义
also, all kinds of incorrect socialism.
各种形形色色冒牌的社会主义
It really tarnished the reputation of scientific socialism.
的确败坏了科学社会主义的名声
But for who wants to seek the truth,
但是对我们寻求真理
for who wants to save the country,
寻求救国道路的人来说
how can you give up the pursuit of scientific truth
怎么能因为有冒牌货就放弃了
just because there are impostors?
对科学真理的追求呢
Right?
对吧
We cannot stop pursuing the truth
我们不能因为安福系
just because the Anfu Club
他们也讲社会主义
are promoting their version of socialism.
就停止对真理的追求
The whole "less on doctrine" view of Mr. Hu Shi
胡适先生主张少谈主义多解决问题
is actually against solving China's current problems
实际上是反对从根本上
fundamentally.
解决中国问题
Moreover, it is treating those who seek fundamental solutions
并将这种根本解决
as dangerous extremists.
说成是危险的过激主义
He wants people to focus more on problems,
他主张多解决问
which is actually advocating improvement over full-scale change.
实质是主张改良
It's putting a plaster on an open wound instead of healing it completely.
不触动反动的根基
It is wrong and won't work.
这是错误的 行不通的
Everyone knows that under the dark rule of the Beiyang government,
大家知道北洋政府的黑暗统治下
China is a lifeless country.
中国是一个没有生机的
A withered society.
枯萎的社会
They would go as far as to turn a school into a prison
他竟然敢把学校变成监狱
to hold patriotic students.
用来关押爱国的学生
In such a society,
在这样的社会里
what practical problems can you solve?
你能解决什么实际问题呢
Use all and every tool you have, but there is still no way
当你用什么工具都没有办法让它
to bring the hope back.
复活的时候
I'm afraid at time like this,
我们恐怕必须
we have to find a fundamental solution,
有一个根本解决的办法
that's the only hope for the actual problems to be solved.
才有把具体问题都解决了的希望
Sir.
先生
I wonder if there is a successful case.
我想知道有没有一种成功案例
One that focused on doctrine before solving actual problems.
是先谈主义 后解决实际问题的
There is.
有啊
Take Russia as an example.
就以俄国而论
The means of production shall be owned by the people.
实行生产资料归全体人民所有
This is the principle of socialism.
这就是社会主义的原理
All those problems that could not be solved in the past,
过去一切社会都不能解决的问题
are now solved.
现如今 全部解决了
According to Marxist historical materialism,
依据马克思唯物史观
the foundation of human society is the economy.
人类社会的基础是经济
Issues regarding law,
法律问题
economics,
经济问题
and the community,
家族问题
and other abstractions,
等等精神构造
these are all like the surface structures of a building.
都属于上层构造 表面构造
Underneath all these structures,
那么这些上层构造的下边
there is economics.
有一个经济构造
Economics is the foundation.
经济构造是它们的基础
If the economic structure ever moves,
经济构造一旦发生变动
then all the above structures will shatter.
上边的构造也会跟着发生变动
So in other words,
那么换句话说
the economic problem is the fundamental problem.
经济间题才是根本问题
So once the economic problem is solved,
所以经济问题一旦解决了
then all the other issues
什么政治问题 法律问题
like politics, law, community,
家族制度问题
women's liberation,
女子解放问题
and issues regarding workers
工人问题
can all be settled.
通通都解决了
Sir, could you speak more slowly?
先生 那个您能不能讲慢一点
We can't catch up to you.
我们有点记不下来了
I noticed that your have so many new insights
我发现您最近对马克思主义
in Marxism recently.
又有了许多新的看法
I'm working on
我正在写
the second part of "My View of Marxism".
《我的马克思主义观》 的下篇
That topic just now,
刚才那个题目
we will talk about it sometime.
我们大家找个时间详细聊
But not today.
但是今天我不想聊这个
Today I want to talk to you about Bolshevism.
我想跟大家谈谈布尔什维克主义
I have declared publicly that
我公开宣称
I am fond of Bolshevism very much.
我是很喜欢布尔什维克主义的
The day when the Allies won,
记得在协约国战胜的那一天
I wrote an article.
我作了一篇文章
It's called "The Victory of Bolshevism"
叫《布尔仕维克主义的胜利》
published in "New Youth".
登在了《新青年》上
Perhaps because some people in Japan
可能是因为日本有人把布尔什维克主义
translated Bolshevism as radicalism,
翻译成过激主义的原因
some people say it is a kind of cruel doctrine.
就有人说它是一种凶暴残忍的主义
That's absurd.
这是非常荒唐的
I have a strong feeling.
我有一种强烈的感觉
The popularity of Bolshevism
布尔什维克主义的流行
is a great turning point of human culture.
是我们人类文化上的一大变动
We should introduce it.
我们应该介绍它
We should study it
我们应该研究它
and spread it to human society.
并把它昭布于人类社会
Just because there all some rumors about it,
不可听信别人对它的谣言
doesn't mean we should just believe that and treat Bolshevism negatively.
就拿残暴的粗暴的话去对待它
Or even eliminate it.
抹杀它的一切
Some time ago, some people said that
前一段时间有人说
after the October Revolution
十月革命之后
Kropotkin was shot.
克鲁泡特金被人枪毙了
But recently there are reports from the West say that
但是近期的欧美报道说
he is safe and sound somewhere near Moscow.
他在莫斯科附近安然无恙
Exactly.
对
This incident helped us clarify
这就让我们更加看清了
a question.
一个问题
What is Bolshevism?
布尔什维克主义是什么
Those who advocate not talking about doctrine,
那些主张不谈主义的
what they aim at is to be against Bolshevism,
自的是反对布尔什维克主义
against scentific principles.
反对的是科学的真理
With people like that around, what shall we do then?
在这种情况下我们怎么办
Promoting an abstract doctrine and studying into the practical problems,
我们认为宣称理想的主义
they are not contradictory, instead they help each other in many ways.
与研究实际的问题是交相为用的
To solve a widely existing problem in society,
社会问题的解决
it has to rely on the common movement of most people in that society.
必须依靠社会上多数人的共同运动
To have a common movement,
而要有共同运动
there must be a common doctrine as the criterion.
就必须有共同的主义作为准则
So it is necessary to talk about doctrine.
所以谈主义是必要的
Without it,
不宣传主义
without the guidance of scientific theory,
没有科学理论指导
there is no way to solve those social problems.
社会问题永远也没有解决的希望
Let more people know about the scientific truth
让更多的人知道科学真理
and use this doctrine as a material,
并把这个主义当作材料
as a tool,
当作工具
to solve one practical problem after another.
去解决一个又一个的实际问题
As for all those nonsense,
至于那些阿猫 阿狗
those who only blabber,
鹦鹉 留声机
let them be.
就任它们在旁边乱响
Radicalism?
什么过激主义
Great disaster and danger?
洪水猛兽
Calling us heretics?
异端邪说
They can say whatever they want about us.
我们就任他们给我们乱扣帽子
Because we don't care about them at all.
因为我们根本就不在乎他们
The methods for rescuing turned out to be impossible.
救济的方法成为了不可能
It has also led to many tragedies in history
也使历史上演了
that did not need to happen.
许多本不须有的惨剧
Which one is professor Hu Shi?
谁是胡适教授
I am.
我是
Director Wu asked for you
我们吴总监
to please come to the Metropolitan Police Department with me.
请您到京师警察厅走一趟
What are you doing?
你们要干吗
Yeah, what is it?
对你们要干吗
What do you want with Mr. Hu?
你们找胡先生什么事
Don't worry, let me do the talking.
别着急 我来问他
What time and what is it about?
何时何事啊
I'm just following my orders.
我也是奉命请您
Please come now.
现在就去
Car is waiting outside.
车已在门前等候
I don't know what it is about.
至于何事我不清楚
Please.
请吧
Sir.
先生
Stay at school.
好好在学校待看
Wait for me.
等我回来
Please.
请
Jialun.
家伦
Sinian.
斯年
We need to report this, go.
去 报告学校 走
Go.
走走走
Professor Hu, please sit down for a moment.
胡教授 您稍坐片刻
Director Wu will be here soon.
吴总监马上就到
Thank you.
谢谢
[Wu Bingxiang, Chief of the Metropolitan Police Department]
[吴炳湘 京师警察厅总监]
Fellow townsman.
老乡
Young fellow.
小老弟
Your reputation is now at its peak.
你现在这名气可是如日中天呀
Seems like you will be able to replace Chen Duxiu soon.
大有取替陈独秀之势啊
Director Wu said we are brothers from the same town.
吴总监唤我一声老弟老乡
That's too much.
我是愧不敢当啊
Why, is that not true?
怎么 我不配做你的老兄
True that we are from same place.
不是您不配
But I can't not even imagine being your brother.
而是我胡适不敢高攀
After all, we are not the same kind.
毕竟我两不是同类
Are you saying I am not a human just like you?
你什么意思 骂我不是人
Director Wu, you misunderstood.
吴总监您误会了
I mean,
我的意思是
we are not the same kind of people.
我俩不是同一类人
We are two people on two different paths.
是两个道上的人
Well, since you don't care about talking about hometown.
那好吧既然你不论乡情
Then let's get down to business.
那我们就谈正事吧
I was just about to ask Director Wu.
我也正想请教吴总监
You sent a car to bring me here.
这么兴师动众地把我请来
What is the reason?
到底是有何公干呢
Please sit down.
请坐吧
Sit down.
坐吧
Brother Hu.
胡老弟
The "Weekly Review",
这个《每周评论》这个刊物
I don't think it's necessary to continue.
我看就不用再继续办下去了吧
What does this mean?
这是何意呀
This is for your own good.
这是为你好
The "Weekly Review" promotes radical remarks.
《每周评论》宣传过激言论
Spreading rumors and disturbing the people.
蛊惑民众 扰乱社会
A serious allegation.
罪名不小
I don't think the Director has the power
我想昊总监并无取消我等
to stop the publication.
创办引物的权力吧
Like I said, it's for your own good.
我刚才说了 我是为你好
Look at these.
再看看这个
These are all evidence material.
这些都是举证材料
My boss has ordered the Police Department to file a case for investigation.
上峰有令 命警察厅立案侦查
I made an exception
我念及你是老乡
and invited you here to talk to you in peace,
所以才特意破例
given that we are from the same town.
把你邀请到这儿来和你商量的
Director Wu, what do you have in mind?
吴总监 你有什么想法
Two ways, you either stop publishing right now,
两条路 一个是自行停力
or you and others will face investigation and ban by the government.
二 立案侦查 政府取缔
I advise you to choose the easier one
我劝你呀 两害相权取其轻
or end it yourself.
还是自行了断了吧
The "Weekly Review"
《每周评论》
is a registered publication of Peking University.
它是北京大学注册的刊物
Chen Duxiu is the editor-in-chief.
陈独秀他是主编
I'm just a temporary custodian.
我只是临时代管
I'm afraid I can't make that decision.
恐怕是不能做主
I have to say sorry to your kindness, Director Wu.
辜负了吴总监您的好意了
Indeed.
正是因为
It is precisely because Chen Duxiu is the one in charge of the "Weekly Review"
《每周评论》的主编是陈独秀
that I want to talk to you about the situation.
我才请你来停办的
Think about it.
你可想好了
The attention on Chen Duxiu's case has just dropped a bit.
陈独秀的案子刚刚有所松动
At this time, an investigation on "Weekly Review",
这个时候对《每周评论》
a new case on file,
立案侦查
it's not gonna help with his case.
陈独秀恐怕不是
Let alone if he can get out or not,
出得去出不去的问题
it will be if he can live or not.
是活得了活不了的问题了
Let me tell you this.
我这么跟你说吧
Your decision doesn't matter.
你同意也罢 不同意也罢
The government will ban it either way.
政府都要取缔
I say you might as well take the initiative,
我劝你还是要主动一些
give all concerned parties an easy way out.
大家都有台阶下
Then, after some time,
也许到那个时候
when things are not this tense again,
就不再追究了
you can always apply to run another new paper.
你要办报可以另外再申请嘛
Director Wu, what you meant is that
吴总监 您的意思是
if now,
如果现在
I stop the "Weekly Review",
《每周评论》给它停办了
Zhongfu can come out soon?
仲甫就能很快地出来吗
Hard to be a good guy these days.
好人难做呀
Why else would I have you invited here?
否则 我把你叫来干什么
Have some tea.
喝茶吧
Director Wu, I'll go back and talk to the others.
吴总监 我回去跟大家商量商量
We will do as you say.
就按吴总监您说的力
Now you see, we are indeed brothers from the same town.
还得是老乡帮老乡啊
Have some tea.
喝茶吧
[Autumn 1919]
[1919年 秋]
Work is labor.
干活就是劳动
Labor is work.
劳动就是干活
Focus on your work, everyone.
大伙都仔细点干啊
Yeah.
好嘞 好
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
Mr. Shouchang, good news.
守常先生 好消息
Just got the message.
刚刚来的电报
"I am fully recovered and will be in Beijing soon."
吾身体已痊愈 近日抵京
"Back to school on the 20th."
二十日到校复职
From Cai Yuanpei.
蔡元培
Good, great!
好 好 好
Now the rescue movement for Mr. Cai has succeeded.
挽蔡运动算是彻底胜利了
All that's left is brother Zhongfu.
下面就差仲甫兄了
Come on, students, work hard.
同学们 加油干起来
Come on!
来
Yeah!
好嘞
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
This is Zhou Enlai from the Tianjin Student Union.
这是天津学联的周恩来同学
They made a special trip to ask you for advice.
他们是专程来向您请教的
Nice to meet you, Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生好
Nice to see you, students.
同学们好
Zhou Enlai.
周恩来
I know you.
我知道你
I read your "Innovation".
你那个《革心革新》我看了
Very well written and insightful.
写得非常好 非常有见地
[Zhou Enlai, styled Xiangyu, editor-in-chief of the "Tianjin Student Union Newspaper"]
[周恩来 字 翔宇 《天津学生联合会报》主编]
Sir, I'm flattered.
先生过奖了
Let's sit down and talk, okay?
咱们坐下聊 好不好
Okay.
好
Please sit.
坐
There are stools here.
来 这儿有凳子
Enlai.
恩来
What's the situation like over there?
你们那边的情况是怎么样的
You might not know.
不知先生是否知道
The police forced us
警察已经把我们的
to stop the "Tianjin Student Union Newspaper".
《天津学生联合会报》给封了
We're preparing for a reissue.
我们正在准备复刊
I heard about it.
我听说了
Recently the reactionaries are acting aggressively.
现在反动派猖狂得很
The "Weekly Review" also had to stop.
《每周评论》也被封了
But our "New Youth"
不过我们的《新青年》
will be back again soon.
马上就要复刊了
We came here with a question.
我们这次来
We want to know your advice on
主要是想向先生请教
how to make the patriotic student movement
该怎样把爱国学生运动
a long-lasting movement.
持久化的问题
Long-lasting.
持久化
Enlai, you brought this question to me
恩来 我觉得你这个问题
at the exact right time.
提得特别好
After the issue of the Paris Peace Conference has come to an end.
巴黎和会的问题结束以后
How to find new goals for the student movement?
学生运动该如何深化
What should we do now?
我们又应该做些什么
This is indeed a question worthy of consideration.
这确实是一个值得考虑的问题
Do you have any ideas?
你们有什么想法吗
In Tianjin,
我们天津
we have two main student associations
主要有学联和女界同学会
and women's associations.
两个组织
Which leads to the potential problem
客观地存在着
of unified command and coordination.
统一指挥协调的问题
So we thought
所以我们想
can we unify these two organizations?
能不能把两个组织统一起来
Among them, the backbone will make up the Awakening Society.
由其中的骨干组成觉悟社
On top of leading the student movement,
除了领导学生运动之外
we need to strengthen our minds with new knowledge and ideological forces.
更重要的是加强自身的思想武装
We should study new thoughts, new ideas, publish publications,
研究新思潮 新思想 出版刊物
and form a core team with the adequate knowledge and skills
形成一个用新思想武装起来的
that can take the responsiility as leader of the students.
能够担负起领导责任的核心团体
I really don't know.
不知道
Sir, do you think our idea is feasible?
先生以为我们这个想法是否可行
I think it's very good.
我觉得特别好
After what we been through during the May Fourth Movement,
经过了五四运动的洗礼
now we are at this place,
我们现在确实到了一个
at a critical moment needing a new guiding ideology.
需要新的指导思想的关键时刻
At such a critical moment,
在这样一个关键时刻
the Tianjin Student Union
你们天津学联
chose to take a brave step to break the boundaries between men and women,
敢于打破男女生之间的界限
to organize the essential members
把这些骨干组织起来
and start this Awakening Society.
成立觉悟社
Studying, researching and promoting new ideas and knowledge.
宣传和研究新思想
I really think
我真的认为
you are now holding
你们是抓住了
the core of the student movement.
学生运动的核心了
I like the sound of it.
我看好你们
I support you all.
我也支持你们
Good.
好
We are hoping that
我们呢 想让李先生
you can come to Tianjin to give us a speech.
您去天津给我们开一场演讲
Share your valuable insights with us, give us the chance to learn.
让我们也陶熏陶
Well, I'd like to go.
好啊 我愿意去啊
But we don't have any funds.
但是我们没有什么经费
For transportation,
路费的话
you will have to pay for it yourself, sir.
需要先生您自己来出
No problem, I will take care of that.
好吧 我自带干粮
Please tell me if you have any difficulties.
你们有什么困难你们尽管告诉我
I will do my best to help.
我来帮你们想办法解决嘛
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
You are welcome.
不用客气
So in this speech,
那么这次演讲
what do you want me to talk about?
你们希望我讲些什么
Whatever you want to, sir.
先生您讲什么我们都爱听
Right.
对
How about this?
那你们看这样行不行
Here.
这个呢
It's my second half part of
将是我在 《新青年》
"My View of Marxism",
下一期发表的
it will come out on "New Youth",
《我的马克思主义观》的
next issue.
下半部分
I will talk about this.
我就讲这个
Marxism.
马克思主义
Excellent.
太好了
Perfect topic.
这个题冒太好了
Want some noodles with soybean paste?
炸酱面吃吗
Noodles with soybean paste.
炸酱面
Of course.
吃啊
I need to go to a meeting soon.
我一会儿有个会就不陪你们了
Shiyan.
世炎
Take care of Enlai and the others for me.
帮我照顾恩来还有同学们
Take them to have some noodles.
带着他们去吃炸酱面
The usual place.
老地方
Longfu Temple.
隆福寺
Big amount, enough for everone.
管饱 还管够
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
Jingtan, you saw the bigger picture
镜潭哪 在对待陈独秀的问题上
on how to deal with this Chen Duxiu problem.
你看得远 顾全了大局哟
Take a seat.
坐
Okay.
好
Come and sit.
来 坐
Jingtan, now North and South is trying to reach an agreement.
镜潭 现在南北要议和了
[Xu Shichang, pen name Juren, President of the Republic of China]
[徐世昌 号 菊人 中华民国总统]
The southern government insists to release Chen Duxiu.
南方政府坚持要释放陈独秀
To make sure this agreement goes through smoothly,
为了不刺激他们
we might as well just let Chen Duxiu go.
还是找个台阶把陈独秀放了吧
Mr. President.
大总统
I have long anticipated this day.
我早就预料到了有这一天
I have already prepared for this day.
所以我留了个后手
Don't worry, I'll do it right away.
您放心 我马上去办
No, no, no.
不不 不
There is more.
我再跟你说几句啊
Chen Duxiu is a dangerous person.
对陈独秀这个危险分子
We are letting him go,
放是要放
not setting him free to do whatever he wants.
但是不能放任自流
Even out of the prison,
就是出了监狱
we need to supervise him.
也要能监管得任
Otherwise, there will be chaos at any time.
不然随时都会出现大乱子
Jingtan, you have experience.
镜潭你有经验
You need to take more cautions in this respect.
这方面 你要多些手段才行
Rest assured, Mr. President.
请总统放心
I've already made a plan.
我早就留有预案
Talk to me.
说说看
First, the investigation on Chen Duxiu
第一 陈独秀立案侦香
has been going on over three months.
已经有三个多月了
We have to give an explanation.
你总得有个说法吧
So, we will say it is a granted bail on the ground of sickness.
所以对外只能说是因病保释
Hence, three sponsors are necessary for it.
这具保人得有三个
They have to be a fellow villager too.
还得是同乡
I volunteer to be one.
我自告奋勇算一个
He shall find the other two by himself.
其他那两个 让他自己去找吧
Second, after he's released,
第二 他出狱之后
there is also the probation period.
必须迷续接受监管
He has to report to the police station regularly.
定期到警察厅来报告他的动向
He can't leave Beijing without permission.
不能擅自离京
If he agrees to these two articles,
如果他同意这两条
we will let him go.
那咱就把他放了吧
Right.
对
Jingtan, that's very thoughtful.
镜潭哪 想得周到
Do it your way.
就按你说的办
Yes.
是
Professor Chen Duxiu of Peking University.
北京大学教授陈独秀
He has been detained by the Metropolitan Police Department for more than three months.
被京师警察厅拘禁已历三月有余
Given that the investigation by the Police Department
近者警厅侦查结果
has not shown any illegal actions carried out by Chen,
终不见陈氏有任何犯法行为
also, considering the three months of prison life
而陈氏因在厅失去自由已久
has caused him stomach illness,
继而引发胃病
he is now released on bail by fellow Anhui villagers.
遂由安徽同乡保释
During the time, his actions shall be restricted.
保释后 行动仍受限制
Any major actions must be approved by the government.
重大行动须得政府批准
Chen Duxiu, you can go now.
陈独秀 具保出狱
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Professor at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学教授]
It's our pigeon.
是我们的鸽子
[9 Jiangan Hutong, Beijing]
[北京箭杆胡同9号]
Dad has no right to let it go.
爸爸没有权力把它放走
Dad is a bad guy.
爸爸是坏蛋
Give Yingying back to us.
还我们英英
You silly children, you don't understand.
你们两个傻孩子不懂
It's good for it to set it free.
还它自由才是真正地对它好嘛
Why are you crying?
怎么还哭上了
How can you know?
爸爸怎么知道
I don't care. I want Yingying.
我不管我就要英英
Let big brother get you a new one.
哥 哥哥给你
How about another Yingying?
再 再去选个英英行不行
A new Yingying.
选个英英
I don't want a new one, I want my Yingying.
我不要 我就要我的英英
Yes. It's Yingying. It's Yingying.
是 是英英 是英英
[Wang Mengzou, Manager of the East Asia Library]
[汪孟邹 亚东图书馆经理]
What smells so good?
这什么味道 这么香啊
Hello, sir.
先生好
Yipin Guo.
一品锅
Hello, everybody!
大家好
Am I not a lucky one?
你们说我有没有口福啊
A big meal right after I get off the train.
我一下火车就吃大餐
I say you have it all planned, coming at lunch time.
你是算计好了 踩着点来的
I am not a freeloader.
我不白吃你的
Here.
来
You are so polite.
这么客气
Bringing gifts all the way here.
大老远还带东西来
Please take a seat.
费心了 快坐哈
Okay.
好
Zhongfu, let me see.
仲甫 我看看
It's okay. Come sit down and talk.
没事 来 坐下聊
Okay.
好
Zhongfu.
仲甫
Zhongfu, see who is here.
仲甫兄 快看看谁来了
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin, President of Peking University]
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
I know, you have suffered a lot.
我很明白 你吃了很多苦
As long as we can win this fight,
只要能换取斗争的胜利
I don't mind some suffering,
再多的苦
I can even enjoy it.
我都甘之如饴呀
Good point!
说得好
We welcome the hero back.
我们欢迎英雄归来
I'm flattered.
不敢当
I just went to the birthplace of world civilization,
无非是到世界文明的发源地
stayed there for a while.
住了一下
What kind of hero is that?
哪里算什么英雄啊
Out of the prison and into the laboratory.
出了监狱 就入研究室
Or go to jail when you leave the laboratory.
出了研究室 就入监狱
This is the noblest life.
这才是人生最高尚
The most beautiful life.
最优美的生活
Civilization from these two places
从这两处发生的文明
is the true civilization,
才是真文明
a civilization of life and value.
才是有生命 有价值的文明
Sir, sit down.
先生 入席
Mr. Cai, please sit down.
蔡先生 请坐
Come and sit down.
来来 大家坐
Please sit.
请坐
Sit down, sir.
先生坐
Thank you.
谢谢
Ladies.
女士们
Gentlemen.
先生们
Everybody.
大家好
Welcome to Mr. Chen Duxiu's glorious release from prison.
欢迎陈独秀先生光荣出狱
The welcome banquet begins now.
欢迎宴会 现在开始
First of all, please
首先请我们的
Mr. Cai Yuanpei will speak.
蔡元培先生讲话
I have been away from Peking University for four months.
离开北大 四个月了
Today, I can see that
今日见诸位
you still hold the same spirit,
初始之心依在
you still have the same ambition.
初始之志未灭
I feel gratified.
倍感欣慰
I want to say something.
现在我就说两句话
The first sentence is,
第一句话是
we would like to thank Mr. Zhongfu.
我们要感谢仲甫先生
It was brother Zhongfu here
是仲甫兄给我们
who lit the torch of science and democracy for us.
点燃了科学民主的火炬
Though I'm afraid that
这把火炬的意义
the significance of this torch
恐怕要在几十年之后
will not be known until decades later.
才能显现出来
It shows us the direction.
它给我们指引了方向
It also illuminates the way forward.
也照亮了前进的路
The second sentence is,
第二句话是
brother Zhongfu, I, Cai Yuanpei, apologize to you.
仲甫兄 我蔡元培对不起你
Sir.
先生
I am saying this from my heart.
这是我的内心之言
Master Cai, I really thank you.
蔡公 我是真心感谢您
You gave me a stage.
是您给了我一个舞台
Have a seat.
请坐
Now we will demonstrate our poems.
下面的节目 是献诗
During Mr. Zhongfu's imprisonment,
仲甫先生入狱期间
we all wrote something
很多先生都纷纷写了
reminding ourselves of Chen Duxiu.
想念他的白话诗
Now Mr. Shizhi
首先我们请适之先生
will read his one out.
献上他那首小诗
At this time, I want to borrow the tune of "Shengchazi"
此时 我想用《生查子》的曲牌
and recite this little poem of mine
吟诵一首我的小诗
to share it with all my friends here,
分享给在座的诸位朋友
and also dedicate this little poem to my beloved friend,
也把这首小诗献给我敬爱的朋友
Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
I'd rather not to miss you.
也想不相思
So I can avoid the lovesickness.
可免相思苦
Think about it several times.
几次细思量
Now I am willing to be lovesick.
情愿 情愿相思苦
Excellent!
棒极了
Now it's Mr. Liu Bannong's turn.
下面请刘半农先生献诗
The title of Mr. Wang's poem is of very new style.
先生的诗 标题十分新潮
It's called "D!".
叫作《D！》
Zhongfu regained his freedom.
仲甫出狱
I am very excited.
我很激动
I am going abroad soon.
我快要出国了
Before I leave,
我终于在出国之前
finally, I see him again.
我又见到了他
I wrote a vernacular poem.
我写了一首白话诗
I'll just read a short paragraph.
我只念其中的一小段
I haven't seen you for more than eighty days.
我已经八十多天看不见你
People say it's separation.
人家说 这是别离
It's a tragic parting.
是悲惨的别离
Is that so?
那何尝是
Our friendship,
我们的友谊
if it were not for those foolish people,
若不是泛泛的仁兄 愚弟
then whatever happens,
那就凭他怎么着
you still see me every day as usual
你还照旧的天天见我
and I still see you every day.
我也照旧的天天见你
The powers has imprisoned you,
威权幽禁了你
yet I'm not confined.
还没有幽禁了我
Countless comrades are not confined.
更幽禁不了无数的同志
And countless brothers coming after us are not confined.
和无数的后来兄弟
Bannong, you are a great talent.
半农你是大才
It's my luck that I met you.
仲甫 幸亏遇到了你
Great poem.
诵得好极了
I heard Mr Shouchang stayed up all night last night.
据说守常先生昨晚一宿没睡
He wrote a long poem.
作了一首长诗
Let's hear it together.
下面我们一起来欣赏一下
From Mr. Shouchang.
先生的作品
Brother Zhongfu and I all had a hard time.
这一趟呢 我跟仲甫兄
It's like a rebirth of a phoenix for us.
算是浴火重生 凤凰涅槃
My poem is a bit long,
虽然说我的这首诗有点长
but I sincerely hope that you
但是我真心希望诸位
allow me to finish reading it
能允许我把它读完
to show my admiration for brother Zhongfu.
以表我对仲甫兄的仰慕之情
Is that okay?
可以吗
You got out of prison today.
你今出狱了
We are all in great joy.
我们很欢喜
Their power, their authoritarianism
他们的强权和威力
all defeated in front of absolute truth.
终究战不胜真理
Prison? Death?
什么监狱什么死
They can't bend your knees.
都不能屈服了你
You support the truth.
因为你拥护真理
So the truth supports you.
所以真理拥护了你
You got out of prison today.
你今出狱了
We are all in great joy.
我们很欢喜
There are many good young people
有许多的好青年
following your steps.
已经实施了你的那句言语
It's either jail or laboratory.
出来研究室 便入监狱
It's either study or fight.
出来监狱 便入研究室
They all go to prison.
他们都入了监狱
Then the prison becomes a laboratory.
那么监狱就变成了研究室
You can relax there.
你便住在这里
As you will never be alone, you will never be short of companions.
不须烦愁寂寞没有伴侣
When shall we start this welcome meal.
这什么时候开席呀
I'm drooling.
口水都快流出来了
Sorry. Sorry.
抱歉抱歉
Sorry for keep you waiting.
来 真不好意思
Let's eat now!
我现在宣布 开席
Here it is!
来来来
Yucai.
豫才
Always pushing the others.
总是催着别人
When is your turn?
你自己的席什么时候开啊
Me?
我
What do you mean?
我哪里有什么席呀
I've been waiting for novel feast from you.
我可是等着你的小说盛宴开席呢
You don't know.
你不知道
In prison,
在狱中很多时间
I spent my time reading your novels.
我是靠着读你的小说度过
The New Culture Movement can't do without it.
新文化运动没有它可不行
You see?
先生您看
I have his food in my bowl, now I am in debt to him.
吃人的嘴软 拿人的手短
Zhongfu has gained the ability to push people for drafts
这仲甫几天不见
in these past days that I have never seen before.
催稿的本事可见长了
Everyone.
各位先生 同学们
I have something to say.
我还有些话想说
I was a child four years ago.
四年前 我还是个孩子
At a dinner party for Mr. Chen Duxiu
在汪孟邹经理为陈独秀先生
held by Mr. Wang Mengzou,
举办的接风宴会上
I changed an ox hoof dish
我把那道黄牛蹄
to a lazy frog.
换成了一只懒蛤
I wanted to play a joke on my father.
本来我想戏弄我的父亲
But today
但今天
I made an ox hoof dish by myself.
我自己做了一份黄牛蹄
I don't know if it's delicious.
也不知道好不好吃
But I want to dedicate it to my father.
但我想把它献给我的父亲
Dedicated to this return to the laboratory from prison.
献给从监狱回到研究室的
Mr. Chen Duxiu.
陈独秀先生
Please accept this gift.
请您收下这份礼物
For it also represents my apology.
因为它代表了我的歉意
Even if there is frog
今天这道菜里
in this plate today.
就算真有獭蛤蟆
I'll still have it.
我也要把它吃掉
Everyone.
各位
Never be satisfied.
苟日新
Always learn something new.
日日新
Always making progress.
又日新
Chen Duxiu today
今天的陈独秀
is still the same Chen Duxiu.
还是原来那个陈独秀
is also a brand-new Chen Duxiu.
又是一个全新的陈独秀
Comrades.
同志们
[Tianjin Student Union Office, Caochangan, Tianjin]
[天津草厂庵 天津学联办公室]
Today, from Tianjin Student Union
今天 我们天津学生联合会
and the women's patriotic comrades' association,
和女界爱国同志会的
ten men and ten women each,
男女各十名骨王
gathered here today.
由于共同的使命
For we share the same goal and the same mindset,
共同的觉悟走到了一起
we set up this Awakening Society today.
正式成立觉悟社
This society
我们的觉悟社
will be the leading organization of Tianjin students' patriotic movement.
是天津学生爱国运动的领导机构
With the spirit of introspection, pratical exercise,
我们的目标是本着
persistence, dedication, joyfulness,
反省 实行 持久 奋斗
sacrifice and creation.
活泼 愉快 牺牲 创造
With the spirit of criticism and mutual assistance
批评 互助的精神
We aim to build a new ideology foundation for students,
做好学生方面的思想改造事业
lead everyone to self-consciousness and self-determination.
带领大家共同走向自觉和自决
Our determination
我们的决心
is to make concerted efforts to walk on the path of enlightenment.
就是齐心努力向觉悟道上走
At the same time, we hope to see all people
同时也盼着社会上所有的人
can find the path of enlightenment.
都能向觉悟道上走
Comrades,
同志们
given the current potential danger of this career,
由于斗争的需要
all names of members in the club
我们觉悟社社员的姓名
will remain hidden from the public.
对外不公开
So, we will draw from the pool
而用抽签的办法
to give each one a number
以号取名
as a code for communication,
用以作为通信的代号
and as the pseudonym.
和发表文章的笔名
There are fifty notes on the table now.
现在桌子上有五十个纸条
A number is written on each note.
每个纸条上写着一个编号
The number you draw
各位抽到的那个编号
is your future correspondence code and pen name.
就是你今后的通信代号和笔名
Let's start drawing lots now.
咱们现在开始抓阄